I've said it before, [music] you never
see a U-Haul behind a hearse. You can't
take it with you.
>> You know, no matter on your last day, it
doesn't matter how much money you have.
So that that that you know, the
Egyptians [music] tried to take it with
them.
>> Right.
>> Yeah. All they got was Rob. Right.
>> Right. [clears throat] So,
>> hello everybody. I'm TD Jake and I'm
extremely glad to have you here at My
Next Chapter podcast. It is so exciting
and so fulfilling that you're going to
listen in today [music] and learn
something that may change your life or
change your perspective as I present to
you none other than the uncomfortable
[music] Denzel Washingtons. Today I'm
joined by a man whose talent has
inspired [music] generations. An Academy
Awardwinning actor, director, [music]
and storyteller. But beyond the
accolades, Denzel Washington is a man
anchored in [music] faith, family, and
service. In this conversation, we talk
about staying grounded [music] when fame
and fortune is trying to pull you away
from what truly matters, why less is
more, and [music] the power of having a
strong partner. And he closes with a
[music] heartfelt prayer that reminds us
where our strength really comes from.
Chapter one, staying [music] grounded.
I think there's a whole section of
people that didn't come to hear me. They
came to see you.
I'm going to take you back to uh many
many occasions you and I have been uh in
conversation. You might not remember
this. You're having breakfast. I think
we were in Atlanta.
>> Four seasons
>> at the Four Seasons. He's just sitting
there having breakfast like people.
And I came down there to have breakfast.
I walked past I thought
is Denzel Washington and we entered into
a conversation
uh that I sat down and we enjoyed and we
had great fellowship and great fun and
you've always been a very touchable
downto- earthth person who seems to pay
little attention to all the tremendous
accolades that have been afforded to
you.
Is that part of the secret sauce that
has kept you grounded and added to the
longevity of your career that you did
not allow the hype to inflate the way
you see yourself?
>> My mother uh God rest her soul. She she
made it to 97.
She Yeah. She just uh passed this past
year and she she owned a a beauty shop.
A beauty parlor, excuse me.
>> Okay. Beauty.
>> She owned a beauty parlor. Not a salon.
A beauty parlor.
And I had done one or two things and I'm
feeling myself.
>> Mhm.
>> And I came in I said, "Ma, did you think
all of this was going to happen and you
know I was?" She said, "What did you
say?"
And [laughter] all the people been
praying for you. She started calling me
superstar.
>> Uhhuh.
>> So she said, "Okay, superstar, why don't
you grab that bucket and go clean them
windows, superstar, when you finish with
that, superstar?" [laughter] So I I got
the message, you know.
I got the message.
>> That grounding is something that's rare
today.
We see people rise up like zeniths and
then crash like nuclear bombs. [snorts]
You have the
the added advantage of looking back over
decades and decades of being relevant.
Longevity is important to success.
When you start talking about longevity,
there are many, many people out here who
want to have longevity regardless of
their profession, whether it is in
corporate America, whether it's in the
faith realm, whether it's on the stage.
Longevity on the stage. I tell people,
the lights are bright, but the heat is
hot.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay. It's been hot.
It's been hot on that stage. Many many
people who started with you melted.
>> How did you make it?
>> How do I what?
>> By the grace of God. I mean, I don't
take any credit for it. It's it's
nothing I did uh as special, you know, u
been knocked down a few pegs and and and
recognized it. But um I just didn't put
me first. I just put God first. and uh
he's carried me [clears throat] through
the ups and the many downs, you know,
the things you hear about and the things
you don't hear about.
>> Mhm. Uh
>> you know when you think about that uh we
were at Taliperry Studios for the
dedication of the Taliperry Studios and
we were talking uh the the Sunday
morning I spoke I talked about the
difference between people who walk
through a door which is an opportunity
and other people who turn that door into
a platform
>> through which other people are able to
access their dreams Without question,
you have had many doors open to you. But
you have also created many platforms and
introduced to the world many many uh
talented gifted people without which
your influence would not have happened.
You didn't have to go that extra mile to
do that. You could have enjoyed the
limelight of the door and walked away.
Is there a sense of fulfillment that you
get out of creating that platform or is
it purely from a business perspective?
>> I I love
seeing other people do well. Always
have.
I I grew up in the in the in the boys
club, now the boys and girls club. And I
was a counselor there. And I I I I I you
know I I I came up in the club as a coun
that at first as a camper and then as a
counselor and I always enjoyed seeing
other people do well. It's it's
interesting that I I ended up in this
business where it appears that you're
out front. That's that's not even my
nature actually.
>> You know, the funny thing about it is
when you think about when when the
public thinks about you, they think of
you as an actor. When I think about you,
I think I think about you not only as an
actor, an entertainer, not only as an
icon in our community, but I also see
you as a businessman. Because what the
public doesn't realize is that
entertainment is a business. And you
have been successful not only at acting
on screen, which a lot of people do. You
have been successful at the business of
entertainment. Can you talk to me about
the business aspect?
>> I tell people all the time, they call a
show business. They should call it
business show. [laughter]
No business, no next show.
>> Absolutely
>> simple as that.
>> Explain it.
>> No, no, no business, no no next show.
And you know, you have to deliver. I
mean, it is a business. It's a dollars
and cents business. Uh, and you have to
deliver
>> and you have to know your worth and you
have to be able to negotiate from the
perspective of knowing your own value.
If other people know the value to want
you, but you don't know the value to
know who you are yourself, it's it would
appear to me it would be quite difficult
to be successful if you don't at least
have some sense of the equity that has
accured behind your brand and
consequently negotiate from the leverage
of understanding that equity. At what
point did it hit you that I am worth
more than how I'm being handled? And how
did you negotiate into the next stream
of opportunities without allowing people
to prostitute what God had given you?
>> I I'm just not
I'm just that guy, you know. I'm not
scared to say no, you know, and you have
to say no sometimes, you know. And uh
it's it's the nose that I've said that
have really gotten me, you know, I don't
know, wherever I am now professionally.
And the the money really didn't scare
me.
>> You know,
I've said it before, you never see a
U-Haul behind a hearse. You can't take
it with you. [laughter]
>> You know, no matter on your last day, it
doesn't matter how much money you have.
So that that that you know the Egyptians
tried to take it with them. [laughter]
>> Right.
>> Yeah. All they got was Rob. Right.
>> So So you you but you can leave it here.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm not just talking about the
money. I'm talking about what God has
blessed me with. I can I can leave here,
you know, and and that's that's what's
important to me is to at this point in
my life just to be in that number.
>> You you uh appear on a lot of platforms.
the uh professor when he inter president
of the college when he introduced you
beginning to talk about you started on
stage not too long ago my wife and I
flew up to New York and saw you on stage
>> nice man coming
>> uh Caesar
>> oh Julia Caesar Julius 15 years ago
[clears throat]
[laughter]
>> seven years ago
>> time flies time flies
>> that was just the other day to me now
that's a blur you you walked out on that
stage and you were back at home again,
back where you started from. Number one,
what made you go back to the stage and
did it did was it nostalgic for you to
be on that stage?
more than that or as much as that is
it's the foundation I had to get back to
the you know like here on stage the
audience will tell you that night right
[laughter]
how they feel about you and and and and
you know it's a humbling experience and
I just wanted to get back to the to you
to the to the foundation between 1990
and 2005 I was doing the best I could to
help my wife to raise our kids and they
were at an age where I couldn't leave
California for weeks at a time, you
know, cuz you can't commute when you
when you're doing a show on Broadway.
So, I just chose not to do to do any
plays on Broadway for about 15 years.
>> Chapter two, less is more.
>> When I saw you uh in the car getting
ready to leave the hotel in New Orleans,
I think you were shooting Safe Room.
>> Safe House. safe house at the time.
To me, that was an amazing uh movie
largely because of the scenes that had
no words.
>> My view, the greatest actors I have ever
seen are people who can convey messages
without script.
And you are absolutely
amazing at conveying
>> an emotion. Thank you.
>> You know, people don't understand the
hardest thing to do as an actor is to
listen.
>> Hardest thing to do as a human being
[laughter] is
to listen. So, and to be quiet and
actually not do a whole lot, right?
>> You know, we think, "Oh, the camera's
on. I got to
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> act it up." Less is actually more. Less
is actually more.
>> Less is more.
>> Please write that down because
>> less is more.
>> One of the big mistakes that I think
that church uh actors make is that they
go overboard. The real pros understand
that less is more.
>> If it feels good to you, it probably
isn't any good.
>> That's the truth. If you if you feeling
so good about yourself, then you're too
self-aware.
>> Yeah. So, you're probably not as good as
you think cuz you too busy thinking,
"Oh, look at yeah, I'm acting now."
>> Yeah. [laughter]
That's That's funny. And it shows. It
shows it shows to the audience. Uh I I'm
sitting there screaming at the TV set
because I was just mesmerized. In fact,
I teased you about it. Uh uh I told you
that you died so well that I was ready
to commit your body to the ground and
that's
>> which in in safe house.
>> Yes.
>> You know what? That's my favorite death
of mine.
>> Y you died big brother. You died
>> that that and training day. Those are
two of my favorite deaths. I
>> I started saying ashes [laughter] to
ashes for as much as the brother was
dead. Okay. This guy died for like five
minutes. He just he just died. I seen
people die all the time. I thought he
was dead. I got my robe. [laughter]
I got my sash and I started for as much
sin as a dearly departed brother's pass
from death. He was gone. And you said to
me at the time, you said I died too
well. Now they're trying to do a sequel
and they can't get me. That's right.
>> And we laughed about it and we talked
about it. It was it was an amazing
thing. Uh when you you uh when you think
of Antoine Fischer, you introduced
>> Thank you. [cheering]
[applause]
>> What was amazing, not not only did you
uh you produced it, you directed it,
you brought new talent to the stage that
we had not known. I think he delivered
one of his greatest performances up
under your
>> talking about Derek. Derek Luke.
>> Derek Luke.
>> And people don't realize a young woman
in there by the name of Viola Davis.
>> I listen I was coming back.
>> Oh, you was getting there. I'm sorry.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I Yeah, I realized Viola
Davis got her start playing his mother.
She plays her his mother in a scene in
that
>> No lines.
>> No lines. No lines. But
>> no, she has one line. You want something
to eat?
>> Yeah.
>> That's all she says. You want something
to eat?
But can't nobody out cry Vape. Listen,
baby girl can cry until she can cry till
I start crying. I don't even know what
I'm crying about.
How How did you cast those two
unheard of people and then direct them
in a way that you got the best out of
them? Because now the reason I asked
this question whether you are in film or
interested in entertainment this is
really about how do you get the best out
of the people you choose in the
positions you hold. So don't just listen
from an entertaining aspect but from an
informational aspect to understand how
do you choose people who are going to
play a role in your organization. A and
B how do you get the best out of them
should help every leader every pastor
every manager every entrepreneur in this
room because some of the time we suffer
because we got the wrong cast we hired
the wrong people. Some of the times we
suffer because we had the right people,
but we lack the ability to get the best
out of them. You have to do both of them
in order to be successful. Teach us how
to do that. Get out of the way.
It's hard. That's that's easy to say,
but hard to do.
>> I can't play the part. Derek played the
part. Biola played the part. Sometime we
want to we want to do it all. Get out of
the way, you know.
Get out of the way.
>> That's a modest answer. It's a I'm not
going to let you off that easy. Okay,
[laughter]
because anybody can get out of the way.
We We can get out of the way. We can get
out of the way. I understand that you
are saying not to try to make the actor
be you, but that ignores the fact that
you had to select somebody who had that
thing in them. How do you look at
someone and see in them things that has
yet to be unearthed out of them?
>> When I'm casting, I always tell the
casting people, I I only need one. I
only needed one Viola Davis. I didn't
need 10.
>> So, and I know it when I see it.
>> Mhm.
>> And I and and I know it when I haven't
seen it.
>> So, when it walks in in the room, then
when she walked in the room, I knew. So,
and I knew. So, it's a gut thing. It's a
It's a instinct thing more than I look
for this, this, this, and this. There's
just
>> Yeah. It's not a checklist. Okay. It's
not a checklist.
You know, I think I know what good
acting is.
>> Yeah. You got to [laughter] know what
good acting is. You got to know what
you're looking for, which is a note
worth taking. You got to know what
you're looking for because I think a lot
of times we don't know what we're
looking for. We interview people, but we
we know the job description. We know the
title, but we don't know the
temperament, the talent, and how well
they will fit into the continuity of our
organization. So, we hire people who
have the right education, but they are
toxic in the organization.
Are you hearing what I'm saying? You
have to know what the temperament is
that you're looking for. Again, you'll
know it when you see it. But whether you
know it or not, you are casting in your
office, in your church, in your choir,
uh in your leadership, you c anybody can
come in the congregation. I don't care.
But whoever is going to be on the team,
I already know what temperament of
person I need in that team. And I'm not
just looking at their bio. I'm looking
at their body language, their
personality, their work ethic, how their
how how congenial they are with people,
how sensitive they are. I don't need a
drama queen running a conference. I
don't need you creating problems. I need
you solving problems. And so I can
clearly delineate what I'm looking for
in the individual. He has a list of
criterias that he's saying that he has
to that he knows in his head that he's
looking for in the actor and that he
will know it when he sees it. You cannot
regulate that over to somebody else.
>> Nelson Mandela said, "A leader
like a shepherd
sends the fast, nimble sheep out front
so that the rest will follow."
not realizing they're all being led from
behind.
So, a leader leads quietly from behind,
>> you know, you don't have to jump out
front and I don't have to out act
everybody and I, you know, we want to we
want to do it all.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, get out the way. Let me show you.
You know, but
that was pretty good advice from Mr.
Mandela.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I would think so. [laughter]
I would think so.
>> Chapter three, faith.
>> [music]
>> When you start thinking about uh
August Wilson, the body of his work, the
magnitude of his impact on the Broadway
stage, off Broadway stage at a time that
black people were not being recognized,
the body of his work ended up in your
hands of which fences is one deposit.
What made you make Yeah. Yeah. Give it
up for fences.
Um, [applause]
what made you make the decision to buy
the body of his work or to own the body?
>> The family came to me.
>> The family came.
>> Yeah. His his his uh widow uh uh
Castanza said the we'd like you to take
care of August plays for us and make
films. I said, I'm just the man for the
job, you know. So that's that's what I'm
doing.
>> What made you give that answer?
>> Because it's the truth. [laughter]
>> What did somebody say was said, "You're
not conceited. You convinced, huh?"
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> It's the I mean, I'm not bragging. I
mean, I was the right one at the in the
right place at the right time with the
right power in the right position to get
things done,
>> you know. And
>> And you got them done.
>> I'm I'm getting them done. I'm getting
them done with the
>> one by one. you getting them done and
then what made you make the decision to
keep so much of his original cast and
take them from the stage to the screen?
These are decisions. What I'm asking him
is how do you make decisions? Because
that has a lot to do with defining the
success of your leadership. How do you
make decisions? And some people hold
positions but delegate decisions.
>> Say that again. Some people hold
>> Okay?
>> And while I want everybody's input into
the decision, my style of leadership,
the final decision is going to be mine.
>> Okay? I welcome your input. I'm not a
dictator. I want to hear your input and
I will adjust my decision if your
information shifts the outcome. But at
the end of the day, I don't want people
making decisions that I have to live
with.
Because at the end of the day, it's not
going to be your name in the paper. It's
going to be mine.
>> That's correct.
>> And I want to know.
>> Am I right about it?
>> Yes, you are.
>> They're not going to write about your
staff. They're going to write about you.
>> And they're not going to attack your
staff. They're going to attack you. They
don't know the name of your staff.
They're going to come after you. And so
you you want to be in you want to hire
people that are smart enough that they
bring you brilliant ideas. But you have
to decide, are those brilliant ideas
worth the consequences of those ideas?
In my world, that's how I do it. In your
world, what made you make the decision
to keep these people who had never been
on screen as far as I know, had always
been on stage, and yet you brought them
on stage. And then I'm going to tell you
what they told me about you.
>> You talking about fences now?
>> Fences. films too.
>> Well, because they were great actors.
Viola Davis, Steven McKenley Henderson,
Michael T. W. They they were all great
actors and and I'm loyal, you know. We
we we got the success that we had on
stage together. Why should I Now, now we
had to we had to recast a little girl.
Uh uh cuz she she uh you know and and uh
and one other part because the kid grew
up
>> but uh
[laughter]
>> they do that.
>> Yeah, they do that. They got it. Funny
how that works. And
>> yeah, it is relieving actually.
[laughter]
>> They keep coming back though.
>> Mine are here so I won't comment. Now uh
you brought them to the stage. I
interviewed them while I was doing a
talk show in Hollywood. This is what
they told me about you. They told me
that you were as much a director,
producer as you were a pastor.
They said you started every morning Oh,
yeah. Of course.
>> With prayer.
>> Right.
They said they were spiritually enriched
up under your leadership because of your
consciousness of God.
>> Well,
[applause]
thank you. [laughter]
>> I now look, I've been on the set a few
times myself. Not nearly nearly nearly
nearly what you've done, but it is not
normal to start the day with prayer.
>> It's not.
>> No. I I didn't hear what you said.
>> It's not normal to start the day with
prayer.
>> Well, I don't know what other people do,
but
>> I mean on the set, I'm not talking about
in your personal life.
>> To have the boldness of faith to bring a
crew together and say, "Let's pray
before we start."
>> I've not seen a lot of people do that in
Hollywood.
>> Or where are we? What town we in? Or in
Charlotte for that. You know, it's
funny. It's funny. People talk about
Hollywood
>> like it's a place where evil things
happen.
>> Los Angeles is a city.
>> There's no place called Hollywood. We
don't all get together and and have
Hollywood meetings and
>> Yeah.
>> Hollywood is a street in Los Angeles.
I'm in the movie business, right?
>> I'm not in the Hollywood. I don't even
know what the Hollywood business is,
right?
>> I don't know how to how to do that. I
make movies. I do plays. I direct. And I
that's
>> that being said and that is absolutely
true and I I I've been on both sides of
the street. I don't demonize what is
called quote unquote Hollywood. I'm just
saying in the course of doing business
not every person in business brings the
cast together and has prayer
>> that doesn't happen. Why does that
happen with you?
Because I was raised, right? I don't
know [laughter] that this,
>> you know. My father was a minister.
>> I know your father was a minister.
>> Father was a minister.
>> He's a PK. Y'all give it up. PK's
>> Church of God in Christ.
>> My mother grew up in uh well,
folks not old enough. Kelly Temple in in
in New York City.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay. My mother grew up in in in that
church and uh
>> see you at home.
>> I see. [laughter]
>> Evidently being raised in the faith, you
still are involved in the faith. You
still have been a a loyal supporter of
West Angeles. You've done some amazing
things down through the years. You uh
have helped Bishop Blake in amazing
ways. You have helped many people start
and launch their careers. You have
financed uh historically black colleges.
You have been extremely philanthropic.
You have a different rhythm
in your soul. Is that coming from your
faith?
>> That's sad that you say that have to
even say that because that's what we all
should should do.
>> Yeah.
>> It shouldn't be. There's nothing
exceptional about
>> should
should [laughter]
emphasis on the word should. But but you
know without sitting here talking to me
that that is exceptional that very few
people have the kind of temperament
especially that lasts that long and
started that young. We have not seen
you. We seen you do sexy scenes but we
have not seen your body. You have not
prostituted yourself in any film at any
time. Oh, you haven't seen all the
movies and you ain't seen a couple of
them you ain't seen.
>> I saw you down to your draws, but I
don't recall.
>> Okay, let's let's keep it real.
>> I did a little bumping and grinding. I
did a little
>> Yeah. Yeah, you did a little bumping and
grinding, but you never you you you
Yeah,
>> that's terrible.
>> Yeah, that's edit this out the tape. But
we going to keep it real for a minute.
You didn't put your
everything out there, [laughter] let me
say it like that,
>> right?
>> To get a role. Why didn't you? And are
you glad you did?
>> I had a mentor uh uh in in college my
senior year when I really just started
acting. And and he talked he talked to
me about never having to compromise,
you know, myself. and and and and
I remembered that that that wasn't
necessary and I I got that guy. I mean,
I I've just been blessed beyond measure.
I found out early in college that I had
this unique ability. So, and things that
were happening in in my life. Uh, I
don't know if some people maybe have
heard me talk about a woman prophesied
when I was 20 years old. She said, "Boy,
you're going to travel the world and
preach to millions of people." She
didn't say, "You're going to be famous."
She didn't say, "You're going to win
Oscars." She didn't say any of those
things. She said, "You know, you are
going to try." By the way, I was
flunking out of college. I had a 1.7
gradepoint average. I was in my mother's
beauty shop. And the reason I was in her
beauty shop was because I was not in
school. I was not in school that
semester. And this woman, Miss Ruth
Green,
uh had this prophecy that that
is coming true.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Well,
>> it's coming true.
>> It's coming true.
I talked to you on the phone
and I told you that I believe that you
have something down inside of you beyond
acting
from a spiritual perspective that is
awakening.
Uh if you agree with that, tell us what
that feels like. And that has shown up
in your work. It has shown up off
camera.
What is evolving in you now from a
spiritual perspective?
>> It it's just that it's evolving. You
know, I uh I remember talking to uh
Bishop Blake years ago. I said, "Well,
you know, what do you do? Should I
should I become a preacher? Should I?"
He said, "No, no, you you have your pull
pit,
>> you know, and and and use it."
>> So, I do have a Everybody talks about a
platform. I got a pretty I guess big
platform or whatever you call it.
[laughter]
>> He got a pretty big
>> Yeah. So I try to try to use it for
good.
>> Use it for good.
>> Use it for good. [applause]
>> Chapter [music] four. A great wife.
Warren Buffett says that if a man toward
the autumn of his life and this is poor
quote of it but pretty close uh has
still maintained the respect
and love of the people who matter most.
He is a successful man.
You live and work in an industry where
the falling apart of the home is the
headlines of the week and people swip
and swap in relationships all the time.
It is a very difficult thing to be who
you are and still be a father and still
be a husband and yet somehow you have
been graced
that the people who matter most
still respect you.
Tell us how.
>> I have a great wife.
[cheering]
>> [laughter]
>> That's the answer.
[applause]
>> Listen, bro.
>> That I have a great great Listen, my
wife is from right here, North Carolina.
>> She was a child prodigy. Mhm.
>> She was the Van Clber competitor, one of
the world's best young pianists at at 9
years old. She was the first black woman
that was supposed to be Miss North
Carolina at a time when they couldn't
let a black person be she she had gotten
whatever Miss Runner up or first runner.
They couldn't even let her be first
runner up because the if Miss North
Carolina fell out, she couldn't go to
all the places
in this state.
>> That Wow.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, her father was an
educator. Uh uh uh they had the one of
the top This was back in segregation
before integration. They had one of the
top schools in North Carolina, the top
debating team. One of the best schools
in North Carolina was an all black
school uh from Newton, North Carolina.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> I I think that's such a great answer.
It's one that I can really relate to.
Having a great wife has a lot to do with
whether you make it through the store.
[applause]
And it's always nice when she's cute,
but it's not nice when she's cute and
not great.
>> [cheering]
>> got a witness somewhere in there.
[laughter]
>> So, a word up to the fellas. A lot of
times you have more emphasis on cute
than great.
>> But what makes the relationship
sustainable is great rather than cute.
And I think that one of the problems
that we have with longevity
is that it is expensive to be a great
woman.
>> [applause]
>> In a world where women spend billions of
dollars looking cute,
>> it is more expensive to be a great woman
because a great woman absorbs a lot of
shock,
a lot of sorrow,
>> a lot of pain.
A great woman bites her tongue.
at times that other women speak their
mind. It is expensive to be a great
woman to know when to speak and when to
shut up and go the other way. A lot of
women who started clapping when he said
that you had to really do inventory. Is
he talking about you? Because because
because
I really do think a lot of the credit
goes to holding things together. It's
unfair. is probably not right, but it
still is true to having a great woman.
We come up sometimes and get the bow,
but really the woman is the glue. At
least in my house, Serena is the glue.
She is the glue and the staples and the
safety pins and the stitches
and everything else. I kid you not. I
kid you not.
>> My My wife
My wife is consistent.
>> Uhhuh. Yes. Consistent.
>> Consistent. She made breakfast every
morning.
>> Yeah.
>> For the children. They they had a little
Bible study every morning. She drove
them to school
>> every morning. So she when I was out
running making the movies and, you know,
killing the lion and bringing the meat
home, hey, cook that. [laughter]
Yeah. Yeah. Cook that. you know, but she
was doing the
>> It might be our generation, but I could
say that I could take your statement and
put it right on Serita, having prayer
with the kids every morning, making sure
everybody got something to eat and still
doing her day and still doing her thing
and still building her business and
still went back and got her degree and
still supportive of me and still got her
hair done. You You have to be a bad
woman to be a great woman.
Multi-talented. In fact, a great woman
is a corporation in one person. She is a
corporation all by herself. If you are a
great woman, you are a corporation.
Whether you start a business or not, you
are a complete corporation. Give
yourselves a hand. if you think you're a
great woman.
>> And and and [applause and cheering] let
let me say this to the to the guys for
the the guys out there. You got to have
vision
to see potential
instead of well, it ain't working right
now. Let me go over here, right?
>> Let me go over here. Let me go over
here. You know,
>> I hucked my wife's pedigree.
>> [laughter]
>> Come on. Her her pedigree, you know, she
she raised me up out the ghetto a little
bit. You know, I had one foot in this in
the street.
>> You know, so it's a balance. It's a
balance.
>> Tell the truth, shame the devil. I'm
with you. [laughter]
>> I was throwing rocks at the penitentiary
now.
>> Yeah.
>> No question.
>> The the thing about it is
at different stages of life, you raise
each other.
Right. Right. Right.
>> At different stages of life, you parent
your partner
>> depending on what is going on at that
particular moment. And people have given
up on parenting their partner because it
has become
uh popular to replace
>> rather than to develop.
[cheering]
>> Chapter five, get out of the way.
>> [music]
>> How much
of who you are affects what you do? Let
me say it like that.
>> I don't know. I mean, I I don't examine
myself.
>> Really?
>> No. No. I don't you know, I know where I
got it from. I know what I'm supposed to
do with it, and that's good enough for
me. I don't I don't keep notes or you
know talk to myself and
too too much about I try to get out of
the way.
>> You try to get out
>> I try to get out of the way. Yeah. You
know uh man man goes down to the ocean.
>> Okay.
>> Tries to fit all the knowledge of the
ocean into his little brain
instead of just jumping in the water
>> and enjoying himself. Faith is jumping
in the water. Mhm.
>> Ego is if I don't understand it, it
doesn't exist. To think we can reduce
everything to our level of understanding
is ego on steroid. How dare any of us? I
know what's best. Oh, really? Okay. Good
luck. [laughter]
>> Yeah. You know, three times since we've
been talking, you have said get out of
the way.
>> Oh, yeah. Okay. And and and if I had to
entitle this this this talk, this master
class, I would have to call it get out
of the way.
>> And and that is so simple and yet so
profound and yet so difficult to do
because often we worship at the shrine
of our own point of view.
>> Say that again. We worship at
[clears throat] the shrine of our own
point of view.
>> Yes.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> He going to be impressed with something
I saying. Oh, come on now. Give and
bring. But really,
I do think that that is actually that is
idolatry at its highest form.
>> Is to think that the way that you see it
is the way that it is. What I try to do
with my life is [clears throat]
is to understand your perspective.
And while other people talk about what
you do, I always wonder why.
I always want to empathize even with my
enemy to make sure that my enemy is not
a friend in disguise
or or somebody who has been hurt in such
a way that they react in a way that that
yes wounded me but not intentionally. I
try not to smack a patient.
Pastor Ar. Bernard talks about that when
when people come to him or come at him
or at anyone with anger.
>> Yeah.
>> First thing you ask is who hurt you?
>> So because that's usually where it
>> brilliant by the way.
>> Yeah. That's my that's my man.
>> Yeah. He's brilliant. Who who hurt you?
That is not generally the first thing we
ask when we are offended. But it might
be a good takeaway to take with you from
this meeting.
>> Instead of deciding, I don't deal with
her. I don't like him. I can't stand
them. They're ignorant. They're stupid.
They're hateful. They're demonic.
Maybe the first question to ask is who
hurt you?
>> Because
I think it's easier to love
things you understand.
And if you can begin to understand the
other person's perspective,
it changes how you pray for them. It
changes how you handle them. And it most
importantly leaves the door open. The
most amazing thing I'm going to preach
to you minute. The most amazing thing
about the prodical son story to me. It's
not the prodical son. I know what it is
to drift away. I also know what it is to
be the elder brother and stay and feel
ignored. I stayed in one ministry for
seven years and only preached twice. And
my big job was to clean the baptism
pools. So I understand the elder
brother. I understand the prodical son
cuz I have gone on a few adventures in
my life. I'll keep them to myself, but I
have. Uh but the star of the text is the
father because
he left [clears throat] the door open
for the son to come home.
And I find very few people in life leave
the door open for change.
Chapter six, passing the baton.
>> You You have in a lot of ways left the
door open for other people to come
behind you, for other people to
experience change, for other people to
have careers. You talked about uh the
level of training that you have. Uh I
talked about the level of training, the
scholarships that you've given to other
people that created massive careers. His
name escapes me right now. the guy who
played in Black Panther that everybody
catching. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> It's interesting you mentioned that cuz
I was about to tell a story about
>> Tell everybody.
>> No, I was I was I was on Broadway and uh
uh uh they had a screening of Black
Panther. So, I told Ryan Cougler, the
director, that I was going to come. So,
I snuck in cuz I didn't want to deal
with the the red carpet. I'm low-key
person. I don't take pictures and all
that. So, I went in the back way and
Ryan Cougler and Chad were were were
there talking
and uh he's like, "Oh, you're just the
person I wanted to see." I said, "Yeah,
I want to see you, too." Cuz he owed me
some money. But but when I sat in the
audience,
when I sat in the audience and and
watched that film,
I understood that the baton had been
passed.
You know, I looked at the I said, "Boy,
these young boys are gone."
>> Yeah.
>> To the tune of a billion dollars that
movie ended up making. I said, "They're
gone." Now, you know, when you run a
relay race and you hand the baton off,
you don't stop. As soon as you hand it
off, you run behind the person. So, I
handed it off and I'm running behind
him, but I know I'm not going to make it
all the way around the track.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, none of us knew that.
>> That's good. that Chad was.
>> That's good right there. [laughter]
That's good right there. That's good
right there.
>> That's good right there.
>> Oh, that's good right there, [laughter]
>> man. I'm ready to go over here and throw
$20 on the altar because
>> But I had to I had to when I watched the
movie, I had to shed a tear. I mean, I
sat there and I shed a tear. I'm like,
man, these young boys are gone.
>> Yeah.
>> You know,
not make anything out of myself, but
Sydney took it a certain distance. I
took it a certain distance and now
they gone.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> They gone.
>> And I I think it
>> And my son's one of them.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. My son is [cheering]
>> That's the greatest feeling in the
world. When you
>> And my daughter, remember I said so.
>> Yeah.
>> Olivia Washington. Just remember I said
so.
>> Yeah.
>> Hey, sister. to to be at this stage now
and not be jealous.
To be at this stage and not be envious.
To be at this stage and be glad to see
younger men and women women coming up
and grabbing that baton while you are
yet running.
You you are not angry or jealous or
competing with them. You're kind of
running to make sure they're okay. Go
on. Go on. Go on. I I enjoy
coaching who's next more than being
who's next.
>> Yeah,
>> me too.
>> You You too.
>> Me too.
>> That stage I find is not always
prevalent in our generation because some
in our generation are still wrestling
with who am I outside of what I do?
>> And if I am not this then I don't see a
role. But I see a clear path. I'm happy
to be Timothy's Paul. I'm happy to be uh
Ruth's Naomi. I'm I'm hope I'm happy to
be Elisha's Elijah
>> because I know what it is to be young
and run and have no one to talk to
>> and have no safe place to lay your head
and have nobody to pull me over into the
corner and say, "Don't slap nobody on
stage." Did you see them? You need
somebody. And you're not really a father
until you care enough to chew me out.
>> And you're not really a son until you
can be chewed out and still come back to
my arms and understand father love
doesn't sound like mama love.
>> And we have a generation of people who
have been raised to the tune of a mama
love.
>> And they don't they anytime you say
something harsh, they see you as an
enemy. and react and fight you rather
than to understand. It takes energy to
care. It takes energy to argue. It takes
energy to confront you. You could have
sat in your seat at the Oscars and let
that go down. But you got out of your
seat.
>> No, I couldn't have sat in my seat.
>> Huh?
>> No way. I could have sat in my seat.
>> No way you could sit in your seat. Tell
me why.
>> That's just not who I am.
>> It's not who you are.
>> No, it's not.
>> And that's exactly my point.
>> Okay. that that you just proved my
point. That's not who I am. You
understand who you are and you're
comfortable enough in your own skin that
you're concerned when another rate when
another runner trips.
>> That's exactly my point.
[applause]
First of all,
it's good to see you. Good to be seen by
you. [laughter]
>> Friend of mine used to say that. I used
to love that. Anytime somebody would
say, "Good to see you." So good to be
seen by you.
>> Yeah, it is good. It's good to see you
after the Oscars, after all the stuff
you went through, after everything you
handled, to jump on a plane, to fly out
here on the red eye with no sleep and
come up on the stage to talk to a group
of people that you don't need and you
didn't have to is absolutely stellar. I
want to thank you for [cheering]
>> this is the this is the this is the I
don't know if I said it up when I was up
here man man gives the award God gives
the reward.
>> Yeah.
>> This is the reward for me.
>> Really?
>> You know
awards are good [applause] but this is
better. This is this is this is food for
me.
>> Good. It's food for us. Is it not food
for us?
[applause]
Chapter 7, Denzel's Prayer.
I hope it doesn't put you on the spot
really, but I'm going to put you on the
spot. And I'll only ask you to do this
because you do it every morning for your
cast and your crew.
I am going to ask you to close this.
>> Let's bow our heads.
Let's bow our heads.
Dear father in heaven, we thank you.
We know that to whom much is given, much
is expected, much is required.
[snorts] And we know that you require
from each and every one of us our
undivided love for you.
You are our beacon of light in this
darkness.
And we say thank you and thank you and
thank you and thank you and thank you
not just for what you've done but what
you are going to do what we can't see.
Thank you for guiding our steps. Thank
you for protecting us when getting here
and and when we leave here today. Just
thank you for all that you've done. And
I pray and I know that out there in this
audience,
I just feel the people in this audience,
Lord. I feel them, Lord. I feel them,
Lord. Hallelujah.
>> Hallelujah. Hallelujah.
>> Hallelujah.
>> I feel them, Lord. And I know that it's
I know you want to touch them all. I
pray that something we set up here
touches them and and and and makes their
relationship with you stronger,
>> better, tighter.
>> Yes, Lord.
>> More loving.
These things we ask in your son's name.
And we pray and we know.
>> We know.
We know.
>> And we thank you.
>> Amen. Amen.
>> You just got prayed for by the one and
only [cheering] Denzel Washington.
>> Come on.
>> Well,
thank you, my friend.
>> It's my pleasure. My pleasure.
>> Hey everybody, I want to take this time
to thank you for watching [music] the
Next Chapter podcast.
If this conversation inspired you,
helped you [music] reflect on an idea or
sparked something new inside of [music]
you, make sure to like, comment, and
subscribe so you don't miss future
episodes. [music] Remember,
life isn't about how you begin. It's
about how you finish strong. So, start
your next chapter with [music] us right
here every week.