If I had my mother and my father at the
same house, I probably wouldn't be here.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I said, [music] "I forgive you
because just maybe God removed you out
of the house,
>> right?"
>> Because I would have been a crackhead.
>> Yeah. By now, you should know I'm TD
Jake and I want [music] to welcome you
to Next Chapter. And I am very, very
excited about the guest that I'm going
to present to you today. a powerful man
in his own rights. He's a popular actor
in Hollywood. Not just one, but two of
[music] the highest grossing film
franchises of all times. He's an iconic
singer, a platinum [music] selling
songwriter, and an awardwinning R&B
veteran. He's also an accomplished
producer, [music] a successful
entrepreneur, a New York Times
bestselling author, and above all, a
devoted father. He remains a true global
superstar. Please help me welcome
Tyrese.
[music]
>> We're glad to have you here, man. I want
to welcome you. The only uncomfortable
part of the day so far is hearing you,
Bishop Jake, read off my Wikipedia page.
[laughter]
>> I am not worthy.
>> Oh, you are.
>> Got so much more to do.
>> Oh, God.
>> I I want to fill in some of the blanks
in between the mountain tops. We covered
the mountain tops in the introduction,
but I want to talk about some of the
other things that you have learned along
the way about life, about family, about
self, and the complexities of all of it.
Chapter one,
recreating yourself. I want to welcome
you first of all.
>> Thank you.
>> To be a part of this great uh next
chapter podcast. You've had many Next
Chapters. You've had to turn the page
many times and recreate yourself and
expose different parts of yourself in
order to have the longevity and the
career that you've had from author to
R&B singer to actor uh to action actor
to all the many many things that we've
seen you do. And it's not easy to be
able to be a chameleon that can fit into
various situations like that. What do
you attribute that to?
Um,
if you've never met a person with blind
faith, I'm right here.
>> All right.
>> No point of reference. See, I'm not the
son of Barry Gordy.
>> Yeah.
>> Anita Baker is not my mother.
>> Right.
>> Gladis Knight. I was not raised in a
house with executives and musicians and
people. I wasn't raised by Will Smith.
>> Yeah.
>> I wasn't raised by Sdney Portier.
>> Denzel is not my father. I wish he was.
[laughter]
>> Right. Because you're being raised in a
house.
>> Yes.
>> Where it's not just the talent, it's the
dialogue. It's the business. It's the
understanding. It's all of the things
that you would hope to say, "Well, if
you're going to take this journey, you
don't have to worry about being
blindsided about what's around the
corner before you get there because
mommy and daddy already had a
conversation with you about the traps,
the things to avoid,
>> right?
>> You know, giving you the heads up, like,
you know,
>> uh, and so
>> blind faith.
>> Um, I cannot believe that's my resume. I
cannot believe that I'm the first in my
family to ever see or achieve or
accomplish the things that God has had
in mind for me. And the pressure that
comes with being the only
>> The pressure
>> is scary.
>> The pressure is scary. The pressure is
real. Let me before I ask you, I want to
follow down that trail. So, hold that
thought. Uh we recently hooked up uh in
Charleston, South Carolina at a wedding.
We've been knowing each other for years
and years and we got together at the
wedding at a [clears throat] pretty
tough time in your life. You just lost
your father. Yeah.
>> And we were able to minister to you and
encourage you. And I wondered in my
mind,
the guy who was sitting on the back of
the bus drinking a Coke or Pepsi or
whatever it was and got discovered and
entered into a career that was
absolutely amazing. Never fully goes
away. Money doesn't take that away.
Grammys doesn't take that away. You have
to live with who you were and who you
are at the same time and learn how to
make a homogeneous connection between
the past and the present and the future.
How do you do that?
>> I don't know. [laughter]
>> I don't know. I've never
>> Is it hard?
>> I've never heard it broken down in such
a scientific way. like you just went
boom boom boom boom and
>> you can't get rid of my point is you
can't get rid of you can't totally
dismiss
your upbringing and your training and
there's a part of you that you learn how
to survive in the world in the streets
in the city and there's a part of you
that had to learn how to survive uh in
California and Los Angeles in the
Hollywood scene and there's a part of
you that had to learn how to do business
and all of them come home with you at
night.
>> Yes.
>> All of them.
>> You didn't leave leave the guy on the
bus. He's still there. And so
>> a lot of people don't realize that. You
get it? A lot of people don't realize
it. So when you find yourself in a
situation,
>> it's which guy does the talking? Who's
in who's going to drive the car? Is Is
it going to be the guy from Philly? Is
it going to be the guy from from
Hollywood? Is it going to be the writer?
Uh how do you manage that? Well,
I think of myself as a a black octopus.
My arms is in 30 different places and
they're all working at the same time.
>> At the same time.
>> And so I'm the head and I'm the heart
and then my arms is just everywhere. And
we're doing things and trying to achieve
things that are all happening in real
time. And each project and its each
situation is in various different levels
and you don't want to lose sight of any
of them,
>> right?
>> Um and then what a blessing it's been
that the singer has helped audition and
set up the success of the actor.
>> Right.
>> And then the actor and the singer has
given birth to the entrepreneur.
>> Yes.
>> And then the coat kid is in the back of
the bus.
>> Yeah. and he's riding the wave.
>> I started this.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm on the bus and we got a lot of
seats and whatever version of Tyrese
y'all end up seeing, we're all headed
that way. And the bus is being driven by
God.
>> My problem is all of my all of my TD
Jake's want to talk at the same time.
And so it just depends on who ask me and
what tone of voice you ask me in which
one you're going to get
>> and what environment.
>> Yeah. And what environment I'm in. And I
have to manage those those people. Uh
the apostle Paul said when I would do
good evil is present with me that which
I would not do. [clears throat] I do oh
wretched man that I am. Who shall
deliver me from the body of this death,
this sin, this this human experience and
all of those people live with you. So
you're in a mansion now
>> and you're and you're eating something
that you ate when you were back home.
Neckbones.
>> That's right.
>> Neckbones in a mansion. Okay. uh
chitlins on China. Yeah. The the the the
the
unique experience we have as a people of
having climbed up and been colored,
we've been negroes, we've been black,
we've been we've been [ __ ] we've
been everything to the point that
there's sometimes an identity crisis,
not just through us corporately, but
individually in finding yourself. And I
wonder, did anybody else ever feel that
way?
Um, yes.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, you're you're
I've had so many moments
in my life
where
I know that I had to dig deep within me
because the things that I have in mind
for me,
you realize that other people don't have
them in mind for you,
>> right?
And so when someone makes it clear, no,
no, no, we don't have that in mind for
you.
>> And I have it in mind for myself,
it won't go away because this person or
this room or this situation denied you
of what you feel like belongs to you.
>> Yeah.
>> And so the appetite, the determination,
it's um the self-t talk.
>> Yeah. Yes.
>> The self motivation.
>> Yeah. the speaking over yourself, the
pouring over yourself,
>> the the
>> you know, and and the thing is
>> I I want to say this, uh I've I've I've
been really struggling with how to put
words to this because there's a chosen
few that will that will hear a piece of
this and decide it goes over their head.
You know, selfish
starts with the word self.
>> Uhhuh.
>> And they've made selfish and being
selfish a negative. But most of us are
giving, doing, showing up for people
mentally, emotionally, physically,
financially, psychologically, and we're
overextending ourselves and giving of
ourselves. And we're depleted. Yes.
>> And we're tired
>> and we're sick and we're wiped out and
we got nothing left for ourselves.
>> Unappreciated.
>> And they don't care to notice.
>> Yeah. They don't care.
>> They don't. I'm here to get what I'm
here to get.
>> Right.
>> And even if you if I wipe you completely
out.
>> Yeah. And so I have allowed myself to be
more selfish
[clears throat]
>> and focus on me
>> and say,
"I'm not returning that text or that
call because I don't have the time or
the bandwidth to be on the receiving end
of what you're about to dump on me."
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So, and then especially when you know
what the phone call is going to be
about,
>> right? So now you got to say,
I'm not going to give you emotional
access to me,
>> right?
>> Because you're going to change the
energy of my day. So I'm going to make
the selfish decision to say if I want my
day to be better, it's not going to
include you.
>> Right?
you will not want to miss as he shares
his personal experience with grief and
losing parents.
You know, when you talked about somebody
like Denzel was not your father, you
didn't grow up in an environment where
you had a model to fit where you ended
up, you know, blueprint. A model.
>> Yeah. No blueprint, anything like that.
I think every man and probably every
woman yearns to have in their parents
some sort of shape uh measurement
pattern blueprint of what they're going
through and what they're going to be.
>> We look from that from our father.
>> Yes.
>> My father got sick when I was 10.
>> He died when I was 16. [clears throat]
>> I realized when I was 30 that as I wept
for him, I was weeping for me.
I recognized that I wasn't just weeping
at the loss of him. I was weeping at the
at the questions I didn't have answered
at the at the things that I didn't have
resolved. You know, did you really love
me? What did you really think of me? Did
you never got to see me win? When when
you lost your father,
it's part of the pain coming from inside
your own house.
This is what's interesting.
When my father passed away, rest in
peace to that brother, to that man,
I went to St. Louis to see him. stage 4
pancreatic cancer. Life was riddled with
alcoholism and crack cocaine and just
never quite got his hands around
figuring it out. And and and
I said to him, I just want you to know I
forgive you.
And and I wanted him to know why. I
said, "I forgive you for not being there
to protect me, for not giving me the
heads up of what's around the corner." I
don't know that he would have been
anybody that would have changed my life
in business or changed my, you know, I
don't know that my father was ever a
Barry Gordy that can sit me down and
say, "Son, don't sign that deal and
here's why."
>> Yeah.
>> But I said to him, "I forgive you." And
then I realized that if my mother, rest
in peace,
messed my life up with the 27 years of
alcohol, the verbal, emotional,
psychological, and physical abuse, and
all of the abuse that was in my house,
and it's still affecting me to this day.
If I had my mother and my father at the
same house, I probably wouldn't be here.
>> Yeah.
So I said, "I forgive you because just
maybe God removed you out of the house,
>> right?
>> Because I would have been a crackhead."
>> Yeah.
>> I would have been verbally and
physically abusive to my mother the way
you were.
>> Yeah.
>> There was other men that came in my
house that ended up doing it to my
mother ultimately. And so I was
introduced to love and I was raised to
believe that this is what love is. Love
is not kind. Love is not gentle. Yeah,
>> love is verbally abusive. Love is
physically abusive. Love is all of these
things that I was raised in.
>> And so I would always find myself
gravitating towards women that I would
be fighting and arguing, being
dysfunctional with,
>> right?
>> And anybody else that any other version
of love that I was in the present of
felt soft. It felt uh it felt uh boring.
>> Yeah.
>> You you ain't argue.
>> Yeah. Well, she must don't love you if
you ain't willing to fight and argue.
And so that's and so I have to I had to
say to him, "Thank you for removing
yourself from my life because if the
crack cocaine and the alcoholism and
everything that you were doing, that
would have all been an impression that
you would have made on my life that as a
grown man, I would have still been
deeply hurt by and affected by because I
would have been raised by another level
of trauma.
>> Right?
>> So, so as an example, you know, people
love to look at you, Bishop Jake, and
say, "Look at him."
>> Yeah.
>> In the mega church.
>> Look at him what he's driving, what he's
living in. Look at him with his wife,
and look at him with his daughter who's
now out there on stage changing lives.
Um and Sarah Jakes who I'm so proud of
and I know you are.
>> Yeah.
>> And
>> but they they they always look at the
fruits and the outcome.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> And even if you make them aware of the
strife and the struggles and the stuff
>> Yeah.
>> that the family had to navigate through.
When you mentioned, you know, I remember
I was preaching and I only had 17 people
in front of me.
>> Yeah. They have no concept no
>> of really wrapping their heads around
that because the version of Jake's
Bishop Jake that they're looking at
>> is on the grounds of 40 books and mega
church and
>> where you are now.
>> Yeah.
>> And and they trap you in how they met
you.
>> That's they they they don't recognize
you wrote 42 books. They don't recognize
that you sold $500 million worth of
movies. They they they want to put you
in a place where they can assault you
with their implications of you. And and
and
>> you are how I met you.
>> Yeah. You are how I met you and you are
who I met you. And that's what I meant
earlier when I was talking about, you
know, you have to live with that guy who
grew up in that volatile home. He's
still in there. Yes, sir.
>> Okay. And money didn't take him away.
No. and movies didn't take him away and
books didn't take him away. He's still
there bottled up somewhere inside. And
then this unresolved issue which I can
relate to. My father wasn't an alcoholic
but I can relate to an unresolved issue
uh with your father
is complicated. At Let me ask you this.
At what point or did you have a moment
that you recognized that you were an
orphan?
>> Yeah.
That hit me a month ago.
>> And how did that feel?
>> The idea of being an orphan
was something that we seen on television
>> documentaries
>> specifically throughout Africa,
>> right? you know, like, oh, there's this
village of kids that are orphans cuz
their mother and father died of HIV AIDS
or, you know, a bunch of bad guys came
in and killed a bunch of people and now
here's these foundations raising kids as
orphans,
>> right? And so when they delivered my
father's ashes to my house
and I was able to put my father's ashes
next to my mother's ashes,
I said, "My mother and father haven't
lived under the same roof
since they divorced."
>> Wow.
>> And now they're here.
My mother and my father never even made
it to my house that I've been living in
in Atlanta for 9 years.
>> Wow.
>> So, this is their first time living
under the same roof with their son.
And then
I thought,
well, at least they're here.
>> Yeah.
And
and then I'm I'm a bit of a a junkie for
the sense of humor of God.
>> Uhhuh.
>> So I'm thinking to myself,
my mother and father are finally under
the same roof with a baby boy.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And my mother died on Valentine's
Day.
>> Wow.
>> After giving birth to an R&B singer. If
you if you're not booked to do any
concerts throughout the year as a
singer, you're likely going to get
booked on Valentine's Day,
>> right?
>> Um, and so there's a sense of humor in
that.
>> Uh,
and then I always have my mother and
father's ashes. I don't always announce
it to everybody,
>> but every meeting and conversation that
I have,
>> I always have my mother and father's
ashes in the room with me
>> because I want them to know how proud I
am of them for doing the best they
could.
Um, [clears throat]
and
>> when nobody's around, do you ever talk
to them?
>> Yes. Yes, I do. It's form of therapy.
>> Yeah. I always say, "Mama, I don't know
what's about to happen, but they pulling
up right now and and and and just cover
me. I know you was always a praying
mama, and I know you still with me, Mom.
So, just pray for me with I I I might
not have the words in this meeting,
right?
>> But I want it to be something." And then
the biggest thing
is
I don't have it all figured out, Dad.
>> Yeah,
>> I don't. And that scares me.
>> Yeah.
>> Chapter three. You may not even know
what to name it, but you may be feeling
it. It's called Survivor's [music]
Remorse.
what God is doing right now.
I've always had this big appetite for
success. Never driven by money, driven
by impact. Mhm.
>> And what God is doing right now with
visions and ideas and dreams and the
things that keep me up at night, I've
had this thing in my mind
and and and God when you pray, I always
say pray specific prayers so that God
can specifically bless you and cover you
for the things that that you're
vulnerable about. Vulnerable about.
>> Yeah.
And so I'm in a place right now where I
am sure that God is about to take me
into these levels and this level of
stratosphere in my career.
And I don't feel prepared
for what God is about to do even though
I know he's about to do it.
>> Right? So now I'm on this mission where
I'm saying I am very specific about I
got to surround myself with people to
cover me spiritually
>> right
>> with the wisdom and the knowledge and
the blueprint and and pour into me to
say okay let's not talk about the winds
and what happens talk about the moments
where you almost wanted to give up.
>> Yeah. Talk about the moments that where
you had to push through the trauma and
the stress and the the press or the
social media attacks or the the
accusations or the talk about how you
got through that. What prayer did you
pray?
>> Yeah.
>> To get through that.
>> Because I I I and I say this in in my
own way respectfully. I I feel like
where I love you, Bishop,
is you have always been transparent
>> about the moments that you wanted to
quit and give up and the struggles
because
>> it's almost like survival's remorse,
right? where it's like everybody looks
at me as being so successful
and all I want to do is make y'all aware
of how hard and how challenging it has
been and how challenging it gets. And
you feel this overwhelming sense of
wanting to really break it all down. And
breaking it all down ultimately gives
folks permission to say, "Okay, I could
achieve it."
People are focused on the net worth and
the plane and the shiny building and how
big the church is.
>> But I don't have a plan. Go ahead.
[laughter]
Go ahead. Go ahead. Maybe that's
prophetic. [laughter]
Maybe somebody will sit there.
[laughter]
Big red bow. Big red bow. I welcome it.
>> He welcomes it. Yeah.
>> Uh so it's it's you know I there's
there's people that that think of
survivors remorse when they they think
of that and it's usually like ah you
know my friend died and we were in the
same car and and I survived and so there
survivors. But the other version of
survivors remorse is I'm more successful
than everybody in my family.
>> Yeah. I knew you win. I knew you win.
You ain't all of that. I knew you when
you were
you know there there there's a scripture
in the Bible that says I will give you
treasures in the darkness.
>> And at first I thought we made it in
life in spite of adversity.
>> Now [clears throat] I think we made it
because of adversity.
>> If if there had not been tension
>> there would be no muscles. Okay. If if
there had not been obstacles, if there
had not been something to prove, if you
hadn't felt invisible, you wouldn't have
screamed out, "I'm over here. See me,
hear me, feel me." That those sorts of
things become of paramount importance.
And also, I wanted to say to you because
you said something uh I think it's on
Facebook or on social media somewhere
where you talked about my wife and I
talking about marriage and how how it
helped you throughout. See, I see. Yeah,
[laughter]
>> I see you.
>> That was like almost 35 years ago.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's just
>> I think God gives us surrogate fathers
and mothers
>> to replace what we didn't have.
>> Yes. Chapter number four. Finding the
right partner. Oh yeah. You want to get
this? What was that like 35 years ago to
get some counsel as if I were talking to
you even though I were talking to a
screen?
>> You were talking to me.
>> Yeah.
>> I seen it on YouTube, but you were
talking to me.
>> Yeah.
>> And and that is that is why we love you
and and
we are so moved by you and your
transparency.
the way you unpacked that conversation
and dialogue and and went into specifics
about the the the working functioning
dynamics.
>> Yes.
>> Of your marriage.
>> And then whenever your wife spoke
>> Yes. I mean to to see you sit back.
[sighs] Okay.
>> Yeah. You know, it was just really like
wow,
>> you know, to to just feel like this
alpha strong
dominant kind of man of God sits back
and he holds his wife at such a high
level of regard. So when she speaks, you
like you disappear.
>> Yeah.
>> And and you want nobody to be focused on
you while the queen is speaking.
>> Exactly.
>> Oh, it was I I I
>> She She is leather and lace.
>> And [clears throat] don't let the lace
fool you.
>> Don't let the lace fool you. Recently,
when I went through that health malady,
I had a heart attack. My wife never left
me for three days or nights.
>> She never left my side. Every time I
woke up, she was staring at me.
>> She She has a tenacity. She had just
gotten over a knee surgery.
[clears throat]
>> Uh we were dealing with all of those
things at the same time.
[cough]
What was really amazing,
she paid her knee no mind. She hadn't
walked on a cane or a walker or anything
since when I collapsed on that stage.
She ran over to where I was. She is
leather and lace. So when I sit back,
one of the greatest one of the greatest
choices we get to make in life is who we
are going to partner with. My God. And
that choice needs to be taken real
seriously because you're going to be in
the foxhole with that person.
>> Yes. And you need to know that when hell
breaks loose,
>> they're [clears throat] going to be
there. They're going to be back to back
and shouldertosh shoulder with you. And
there and you're going to be comfortable
>> with that closeness, you know,
vulnerability. Yeah. Because all of us
bring baggage. All of us had a a bus
moment. All of us came out of out of
some sort of pit or hole or trouble.
Even even wealthy successful people, we
have a tendency to think that if people
went to Ivy League schools and if they
they went to private schools, they had
no trauma. That's not true.
>> No.
>> Trauma knocks on every door. Yes.
>> And when you get your trauma and my
trauma mixed together, they either find
a way to fit together and it becomes a
key and a lock
>> or they clash together and we spend the
next 10 years fighting each other like
we're in the Vietnam War.
How did you know?
>> That's a good question. That's a good
question.
>> Because because and and my question is
coming from this place.
I've been married and divorced twice. My
divorce sadly has played out for the
world to see. Child support, baby mama
drama on full display. I'm almost like
the poster child at this point. And and
I've I've been proud to be able to speak
up and speak out about, you know, family
law, court system, and if you were born
a man, you walk in the courtroom,
they've already had a preset menu as to
what the outcome of this situation is
going to be. It does not matter what you
say or do or how fancy your lawyer is.
But how many relationships were you in
that allowed for you to say, "Okay, well
that was not it." And then that one was
not it. And then when you got to the
presence of your wife, how did you know
she was the one?
>> Well, first of all, I was a Christian. I
had the Holy Spirit. I had the inkling.
That doesn't mean I floated around the
room and had halos over my head. I was a
man. Okay. [laughter] Okay. I used to
tell my wife, there's a man up under
this robe. Okay? But but but the reality
is there is a knowing
that is spiritual. And this is what you
know it's it's not she's fine though she
is. It it's not her voice though she's
got the voice of velvet. It is
that we will always be friends,
that that I will always be for you, that
you will always be for me. I might screw
up, you might mess up, we might go
through hell, we might be under a
diialysis machine, but if you're on a
diialysis machine, I will have your
back. that that that feeling of
connection
>> especially when you grew up without it.
>> Yes sir.
>> It becomes extremely important to know
that you're not connected to my job, my
career, my name, my money, my fortune,
my education, my intellect or whatever
it is [clears throat]
that you really are into me. And the
problem is when you've never had that, a
lot of times you will repel it because
you're not used to it.
>> Wow. you will repel it and give it up
for somebody who fights like you said
and give it up for somebody who gives
conflict because we tend to be creatures
of habit and recreate situations that we
grew up in because we're at home in
hell.
>> If you were born in hell, when you go to
hell, you're at home.
>> Okay? So the first thing that has to be
broken and you have to break this is the
hell [clears throat] you were birthed in
and when you when you break out of that
and you finally decide that I deserve to
be loved
and I deserve to be treated well and I
deserve to have good things in my life.
And you stop self- sabotaging anybody
who cares about you because you have
this inner conflict going on that they
had nothing to do with, but they
inherited when they got you. When you
get real with you and you find somebody
who will sit there and listen at you and
talk to you and talk you down and get
you together and no, I'm not talking to
the star. I'm not talking to the actor.
I'm I'm talking [clears throat] to uh
the guy on the back of the bus because
he's he's still in there. Whoever
marries you marries all nine versions of
you.
>> Praise God.
>> Yeah. Because you can't act all the
time.
>> Pretty soon you have to take off the
mask with no lines. You have to be who
you are, who you really are. and uh
finding somebody who can embrace all
sides of you and then learning the
language to be able to explain yourself
to the person who is confused by your
behavior. When you learn the language to
say,
I know this is crazy about me and I may
not always be this way and I may outgrow
it, but when you do such and such a
thing, it scares me.
>> It triggers me.
>> It triggers me. Yeah. That that that's
what therapy gives you is language.
>> Yes.
>> It doesn't always give you cures. But it
does give you language.
>> Let me let me verbalize what I'm
feeling.
>> Yeah. Because if until you verbalize it,
you can't get it out.
>> Yeah. So you you got me counseling with
>> No, no, no. This is this is I came here
just for this. You feel it?
>> Oh my god. I you know, one of the things
I want you to know
um
that I'm like literally inspired by and
and I can speak for me and everybody
when it comes to you and your first
lady,
the level of regard
that y'all have for each other,
the level of nurturing and like while
you're preaching, your wife is at full
attention.
>> Yeah. Yeah. as if she didn't just arrive
with this man that's up here preaching
and she ain't going home with this man
preach. She's on the front row on high
alert like never it doesn't feel like
neither one of you guys have allowed
yourself to get too familiar.
>> No. No. and and there's such a honor and
decency and respect and covering around
that. And and so what you just shared
about when you had that moment on stage
and she had just had her own knee
surgery and every time you opened your
eyes, she was awake.
>> I'm not even surprised.
>> She threw that cane and ran out to meet
me. She ran a and I give her the credit
because you know uh generally when you
get married one of you is gifted and the
other is crazy. I'm the crazy one. Okay.
[laughter]
I'm the crazy one. But there's got to be
somebody stable who's consistent. But
you know most creative people are a
little bit weird. Okay. And so that
creativity that makes you walk into an
empty room and see it with brick on the
wall and stone on that wall and this
painted over here. creativity, that
imagination works for and against you.
>> Praise God.
>> Yeah. It gives you an idealism that is
hard for people to reckon with because
my wife can't see it till it's there.
>> I can walk into a dump and see a palace.
>> I'm I'm going to put the pool over
there. I'm put this over here. I'm gonna
do, you know, I got it in my head what
I'm gonna do. Yeah. I I dressed myself.
Yeah. I can see I know how I want it to
go. So [clears throat] opposites attract
but the very thing that attracts you
later repels you
>> because [clears throat] their steadiness
starts to feel like boring
>> and and your excitement starts to feel
like wow. And if you make it over that
hurdle,
>> if you make it over the hump, I figured
out that we're losing each other in the
turns of life. If you make it over
menopause and midlife crisis and make it
over surgeries and make it over grief
and make it over accidents that that
grief you went through
>> that's s that's got side effects.
>> Oh yeah. Absolutely.
>> You know it's it's like
>> the only person that's Yeah. The only
person experiencing that is the person
that's intimately with you every single
day.
>> It every day and all the versions of you
and how it expresses itself in anger and
fear and tears and and and can you
afford to break down and still be
respected in the morning. Those are the
kinds of things we we we got to do. But
I got to get I got to get through this
because
>> Well, I I wanted to say one last thing
if you don't mind.
>> Say it if you want.
>> I just want to say thank you.
I want to say thank you.
I want you to know how often I actually
pray for you.
>> Thank you.
>> And I'm saying thank you
because
you have literally changed this place.
You have decided
and God has been so present over your
life.
You have been a vessel. The messages
that got your cell phone tower into
Jesus is so strong. I I'm I'm sure that
at this point when you get out on stage
and you and you speak, you probably have
a couple bullet notes on on the topic
and everything that happens in between
them bullet notes,
>> you're channeling in real time on stage
>> and everybody in the audience leaves a
very different person than they showed
up as because you have allowed God to
speak through you and and display the
fullness of you, the good, the
transparency, the challenges, the ups,
the downs,
>> even your daughter having a child at a
young age. I mean, it what what do we
do? And you
>> you have
you have reinvented yourself over and
over and over in front of us. And I want
you to know
that I pose this question all the time.
Okay. All right. I'm ready. I'm ready.
>> Chapter number five. Material
possessions. Are they all they're
cracked up to be? Let's see what Tyrese
[music] has to say.
>> When I speak in front of folks, I I say
by a show of hands,
uh, can anybody in here that's behind
the cameras in this interview, can
anybody in here right now, if you if you
know what was the net worth of Dr.
Martin Luther King when he was
assassinated. Can anybody tell me what
was in his bank? Don't Google it. Don't
chat. GPT. Anybody know? No hands. What
was the square footage of Dr. Martin
Luther King's house when he was
assassinated the day he died? What was
the rim size on his car? Anybody know
the brand of car he was driving or how
many cars he had?
Okay. So in my mind,
we are not here to inspire people from
materialistic possessions,
>> our net worth, what we drive in, the
square footage of our house.
We are here to empty ourselves of
everything that we can to give people
permission to be great, to pull them up,
to pour into them, to to activate
something inside of them that could give
them purpose to to pour into a prison
inmate
and say, "I'mma get out of here one day,
and I'm going to decide to be great when
I get out of here because Bishop TD DD
Jake showed up with the prison ministry
and poured into me what God has done
through you through it all.
>> I just have to say thank you.
>> Wow. I often have a saying
the real message that I bring to you is
that God can do so much with so little.
I [clears throat] honestly
that that's the that's the story that he
can do so much
with so little that everybody is
eligible because if he could use me, he
could use anybody. Okay? Honestly, trust
me, this is truth before God.
[clears throat]
If if if he could you you know how our
grandmothers and great-grandmothers
could could make cornbread without eggs
and and and then take powdered milk and
make pancakes, stuff like that. That's
what he did. He took nothing.
>> He took mud and made a man
>> and he's still shaping and he's still
forming and he's still blowing and he's
still breathing. And and the the reason
that that I am a Christian is not
because I have perfected being
Christlike. It is that my only hope of
being formed into something usable was
the nostrils of the God that breathed
the breath of life into me. So please
know that. Please know that I am not
this exceptional person. I had the same
pain, trauma, life, crisis, confusion
that you do.
>> Same exact thing.
>> But you're able to verbalize it.
>> I can I can verbalize it.
>> And that gift of verbalizing it. Yes.
>> And but understanding.
>> Mhm.
>> If we're talking about a teleprompter.
>> Yeah.
>> Go read those same words on that
teleprompter. And I promise it won't
have the same. and Bishop TD Jake would
read
>> because I am in touch with myself.
>> Praise God.
>> I am definitely in touch with all parts
of myself and and most people most
people lie to themselves and they
present the version of themselves they
wish they were.
>> And they're not in touch with all of
themselves. So you can't do a 360 if
you're determined to be a 180.
Chapter number six gets real personal
[music]
when he starts to talk about a public
divorce. Can you imagine?
Dion and Tyrese's daughter,
your your daughter living with you. I
understand Dion tweeted something in
response to fathers raising daughters
that impacted you. Have you ever talked
to Dion about raising kids after a
divorce and being a a single father?
>> Um, yes. We we've had conversations. Um,
you know, it there's a lot of single
fathers, a lot of single mothers. Mhm.
>> Um,
and so it it what's what's always
interesting for me is
I know what
I want to talk to my daughter about.
>> Mhm.
>> I struggle with when.
>> Right. So
when when you know that certain things
are being said about you, when you know
that you're being put in a certain
light, when you know what's being
written in court documents that will end
up being posted on TMZ,
>> right?
>> You have to live with that.
and and now
social media and people in their
comments.
My goal is, okay, this is what's being
said, but I just got to figure out when
I'm going to have the conversation with
my daughter because I got to mentally,
emotionally,
physically, and psychologically protect
you. Um, and so we've been having a lot
of fun with with uh the stuff that looks
a certain way.
>> And then once I do my part as a father
and I set her down, I have these
conversations, then she looks at things
through a totally different lens.
>> There's nothing like loving a daughter
that changes how you handle a woman.
>> Wow. [laughter]
There's nothing like it. There's nothing
like it that that that your girlfriend
is somebody's daughter, that your wife
is somebody's daughter. You don't really
get it until you have a daughter and and
and allow that daughter to speak into
your life. Now, I'm I [clears throat]
don't want to put you on the spot. I'm
very protective of people. If you know
anything about me at all, I'm extremely
protective of people. But I understand
you had a conversation with Holly Berry
uh about divorce and about child
support. As much as you are comfortable
>> Yeah.
>> with talking about that.
>> Can you share something with me?
>> Yeah. Well, I I what I what I said to
her uh it was on my Instagram. I posted
it.
>> Okay.
>> And so it is public knowledge what I
posted. Um, but it was actually on the
topic most recently. It was about her
saying that her current
uh better half has been asking her to
marry her cuz they've been together for
a while now and she has been struggling
with the idea of ever,
you know, allowing herself to marry
again. Um, so and I said, well, I could
relate to that. You know, I've been in a
relationship now with my lady Zeli for
five years.
>> And she's always hinting at marriage.
And some people will say, "Oh, you're a
band-aid. You're just filling in the
blanks." And you know, uh, you know, at
a certain point, he's going to dispose
of you and then go find the woman that
he actually wants to marry. But people
don't understand is that your opinion is
formulating from things that you have
never experienced.
>> Right? You don't know what it's like to
wake up, get married, have a prenuptual
agreement in place, have the prenup to
get cracked where you end up paying all
of her legal fees and my legal fees. And
now I'm paying all this money to
attorneys trying to protect what I have.
And then you realize that somebody
marries you and then they said, "I don't
want to be here anymore." And then they
trying to take everything that belongs
to you with them.
And it is really a painful process.
And so, well, hey, if we could be happy
and we could be together and we could
not get married because if you ever
decide that you don't want to be married
anymore, now you're going to be another
person trying to take everything that
I've worked my butt off for for the last
30 years. And what does that look like?
and how long is this going to last
before the judge decides this is my
final judgment? So everything about my
last divorce took 4 and 1/2 years. I
lost all of my appeals in the lower
courts. Then I lost all of my appeals in
the Supreme Courts. And so I had like
three weeks to cough up almost $1.2
million that I did not have to give.
And then who do I turn to,
>> right?
>> When I'm financially
depleted,
>> right?
>> I was doing all right financially until
this divorce turned in the 4 and 1/2
years.
>> I got this calculator in my head that's
adding up all the trauma we have talked
about and it's it's smoking.
It's smoking. The batteries are burning
from from uh the experience you went
through with your mother
to the death of your father
to the crisis of three relationships
[snorts] to trying to figure out how to
raise a daughter.
>> Two daughters,
>> two daughters while you're trying to
heal your yourself.
How how do you cope with feeling and
everybody having an opinion about all
the stuff you're doing? You're crying on
the internet and everybody's making fun
and
how do you cope with being
misunderstood?
Um,
I've gotten comfortable with being
misunderstood
and I've been the beneficiary
of being misunderstood
because when people don't understand
you, they want to stay away from you.
>> Okay?
>> Oh, he weird. He this, he that. Oh,
thank you.
Um, I would rather be at dinner for 3
hours for Bishop G TD Jake.
>> Uh, because at this point I value my
time. I value my mental health. I value
the people that I allow in my space.
>> Mhm.
>> And so I have this very simple saying.
If I do a lunch or a dinner with you and
I leave the same person that I showed up
as,
give me my three hours back.
>> Yeah.
>> My goal in life at this point is to
become very intentional about who I
allow in my personal space, who I who I
allow myself to exchange with. Um, and
this is not money. This is not about
like, you know, everything about who I
spend time with has to be connected to a
mission. How we going to get to the
money? No. Because most of the most
life-changing moments and exchanges that
I've had over my 46 years
has nothing to do with having
conversations about how to get to the
money.
>> Mhm.
>> You know, I don't know what I don't
know. And I am afraid at this point of
what I don't know. I need somebody to
love me into a better me. Give me the
heads up of what's around the corner.
Talk to me in great detail about the
choices and the mistakes, the
shortcomings, the things that you were
blindsided by. the the the charm, the
charisma, the undiscovered magicians
that know how to create all the smoke
>> and get you to think and believe that
they are what they appear to be. And
then when the smoke clears, this is what
their intentions were.
Love me in a way that's connected to
protecting me because I'm tired of
crying.
I'm tired of coming close to losing it
all. I'm tired of living and being on
edge. I'm tired of I'm afraid of what I
don't know. And who's going to love me
enough? Who's going to make me a choice
and say, "Let me love you to protect you
from all the things that you don't
know."
>> Chapter number seven deals with life
after divorce. It deals with current
relationships.
So, if you didn't have a point of
reference at home in the arms of a
mother or sitting on the lap of a father
and you didn't have a point of reference
in the three relationships, not saying
it's their fault, but it didn't work
out. What's different about this one
that gives you the hope
of of finding the love that little boy?
I'm not talking about the grown man, the
actor who's fast, driving fast and
furious. That
has anybody ever loved your little boy
and and do you think you found that
person?
>> What's interesting? Here's the best way
I could answer that because you're
speaking for a lot of men. There are a
lot of men who feel the way you do.
>> Wow.
I um I don't know how much I could
connect to the current relationship that
I'm in
>> and this capacity.
I'm actually s surprised and shocked
that my relationship had lasted this
long because
it started with flirting. Then it went
into trauma bonding
>> and then it became just maybe God made
you an assignment over my life and I'm
an assignment over yours. Um I showed up
broken. She showed up broken. Um, we
showed up with baggage,
lots of baggage, but we made the
decision that we're going to love each
other enough to stand here and help each
other unpack.
>> Okay?
>> I'm not going to judge you with the
baggage that you showed up with. Don't
judge me with mine. We might argue and
disagree about some of the stuff that
that that's pre-existing traumas that
we've brought into the relationship.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And so
what do we do about where we are and
what we have? And guess what? If we
ultimately have made each other better
we supposed to be in each other's life
for just this period
>> because we were here to prepare
ourselves for who else is supposed to be
here.
>> Yeah. Or or did we go through all of
this live unraveling?
Your parenting issues, my parenting
issues, relationships that have put
triggers and boundaries and trauma. No,
nobody ever talks to me that way. No one
ever makes me feel, you know. So now I'm
now moving and operating within the
comforts and discomforts of your past
experiences. I call it marrying your
nurse.
I call it marrying your nurse. The
person that you went to to get well, you
don't recognize that they're scaffolding
and not the building. [laughter] Okay?
And you walk off tearing up the building
and living in the scaffolding and and
it's hard to determine which one is
which. Uh a lot of prayer, a lot of
discernment. Uh, I I took every uh I
took my wife to every old woman I could
find,
>> including my grandmother.
>> Wow.
>> Let the smoke because nobody knows a
woman like a woman.
>> Yeah.
>> Nobody knows a woman like a woman. And
and and there are women who have the
same kind of trauma stories that you
have and have been through the abuse
that you have. And when those traumas
clash,
the house burns down. sometimes with the
kids in it. So, you can't afford to
marry the scaffolding
after you build the house. Wow. Yeah.
Yeah. Some people are in your life for a
season.
Some people are in your life for a
reason. And some people are in your life
for a lifetime. I don't know what
category she fits in, but you got to
figure that out. And you got to figure
that out soon because
you're getting older.
>> Yes, sir. and you're running out of
time. And I say that with a face full of
gray hair [clears throat]
>> that that
if you don't figure it out quick, it
ain't going to matter in a minute.
>> You just said something.
Some people are in your life for a
reason. Others are there for a season.
And it's important to recognize when
people's seasons are over.
>> Right.
>> There's an expiration date on loyalty.
>> Uhhuh. Some of us want to hold on
and hold on and hold on. And you know
that this relationship is at capacity,
right? It's hit a wall. Nothing about
this season that you're in right now
makes sense to proceed with this person,
but you want to hold on because you're
familiar with it.
>> Yeah.
>> And so I've I've wrestled with all of
those things. Yeah.
>> But it all goes back to this and and I'm
I'm a I'll put a button on this.
Irregardless
of what me all may think or believe,
we've created a checklist.
>> Okay.
>> What she looked like.
>> Uh-huh.
>> The the boom boom and the cow cow and
>> you know what she dressed like, what she
looked like, what her net worth is. You
know, women they call them a checklist.
Uh-huh.
>> Men have checklist, too.
>> Mhm.
>> And I've went into this relationship and
I said,
"This woman does not check off a lot of
boxes for me." And yet for the women
that I did say has the majority of those
checklist,
where are they at now?
>> Right?
>> I could not have been more wrong.
And so maybe God in the equation of this
woman has said, "You thought you had it
all figured out, but I'm going to send
you something that doesn't look, doesn't
walk, doesn't talk, doesn't have any of
these things according to this checklist
that I've created." Next thing you know,
we're at 5 years and I'm with this woman
right now in a relationship that lasted
longer than my last marriage. Wow.
Chapter number eight. You think it's
just a movie or a show, but it's really
a business. Show business. Tell me about
the role you wish you'd have took that
you didn't.
TV, film, whatever, and you look back at
it and say, I should have took that.
Well,
I I I don't really know if there's a
role I should have took
that I struggle with over the role
>> that you did
>> that I'm determined.
>> Oh,
>> to still do.
>> Okay.
>> The life story of Teddy Pendergrass.
>> That's the movie that keeps me up at
night.
>> I was the Paul Bear at his funeral. I
was I was with him for at least 6 years
prior to him passing away. And he said,
"You're the only person that could play
me in a movie because even though you
sing and you act, you never wanted to be
me." And he's like, I would never want
anybody to play a role of me as Teddy
Pendergrass who groomed and nurtured and
tried to sound like me, look like me,
perform like me. You were you the whole
time and that's why I want you to play
me in the movie.
>> So Lee Daniels is attached to directed
because him and Teddy are both from
Philadelphia.
And [snorts]
so, you know, it's it's in a gray area
right now. There's some stuff that's
going on creatively that's kind of put
the project on hold. But I hope and I
pray that I'm able to keep my word that
I gave him that I'm going to tell his
story.
>> What kind of man was Teddy Pendergrass?
>> He was a good man.
>> I grew up my brother used to have these
eight tracks with Teddy Pendergrass on
them and he would turn them up all the
way to 10. Yes, sir.
>> And play them. And he was the man.
>> Yes, sir. famous incidentally for
wearing white suits and you got on a
white jacket and and he he performed
>> with his cowboy hat.
>> Yeah. When I met him, he was in a
wheelchair doing gospel plays.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh you you watched his deterioration.
There's nothing like deterioration to
show your inner ingredients. M
[clears throat]
>> in in a word or two without divulging
anything private or personal,
>> what kind of man was he?
>> Charm. Charming. Charismatic.
Um,
you know, I I've been around my share of
people,
>> right,
>> that are in a wheelchair,
uh, or living with some type of terminal
illness.
And you'd be surprised at how often they
go out of their way to make sure that
nobody feels sorry for them.
>> Right. Right.
>> And Teddy was that guy. Don't feel sorry
for me. What's going on? How you doing?
Oh, yeah. you know, whatever you going
through. I mean, you ain't going through
this,
>> right?
>> You know, so he'll be the one to give
you some perspective while he's laying
in the bed quadripollesgic, paralyzed
from the neck down,
>> right?
>> And then you leave there and you go,
"Well, yeah, you know, he he gave me
some perspective that I did not have,
but yeah, he didn't want anybody to feel
sorry for him and his condition, his
situation. He'll have conversations with
you about it.
>> But he he never wanted you to leave
feeling sorry for him cuz
[clears throat] he found strength and
and the choice that God kept him alive
as long as he kept him alive because he
could have died in that accident.
>> There is a certain fraternity that seems
to exist amongst talented actors,
singers, what have you. Uh either it's a
very good fraternity or they're beefing
at each other. You've seem to have had a
great fraternity and and and what about
the rock? Tell me about the rock. 60
lbs. He lost 60 lbs. I saw him on TV. I
almost didn't recognize him.
Tell me about that. How number one, how
hard is it? Uh and uh
is he going to gain it back?
>> I I don't I don't know anything about
his weight loss. Uh I seen it online
like everybody else. I'm not in touch
with him to call him and have a
conversation with him about,
>> but I I it's my understanding that he
lost all the weight for a movie role
when he was playing a wrestler of some
sort.
>> Um, and yeah, I'm I'm sure if he lost
all that weight for the role, then he'll
probably be putting it back on for his
You probably don't remember this, but
that's one of the first things you told
me in California when we were going out
to eat. How you eat sometimes and and
gain weight and do what you got to do
and then go in the gym and work it off.
So you Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's back in
your uh baby boy days. Yeah. Yeah. We
ain't even we ain't even going there.
We're going to stay out here where the
air is fresh. Uh
>> what was Will Smith's advice to you?
Will Smith uh said, "You can often tell
how far your life and career will go
based on the five people you spend the
most time with."
>> Wow.
>> So, if you have a problem with your
life,
you should have a problem with the five
people that you have surrounded your
life with. If you're out of shape, you
likely reflect the group of people that
allowed for you to look that bad.
What you're doing, what you're not
doing, the direction you're going in,
what direction you're not going on going
in is all a reflection of the five
people that you spend the most time
with.
>> That's a profound statement.
>> Oh yeah. That's worth writing down
>> and remembering because sometimes it is
easier
>> to see your brother than it is to see
yourself.
>> That's it.
>> And sometimes seeing him helps you to
see yourself. I only got one more card
and I I'll be done.
>> Chapter number nine. I couldn't let
[music] Tyrese go without asking him.
How's your mental health?
>> How is your mental health today?
Um,
fragile.
>> Okay.
>> Um,
I
>> That's a terribly honest answer.
>> Yeah, it it's fragile. It's fragile
because
I'm still
processing
my divorce. Mhm.
>> Um I don't like where I am financially
because of a 4 and 1/2 year legal
with all it's it's it's bad. Um
and at the same time
my life
could only I I feel like
h how [clears throat] could I say this?
I I really want to encourage somebody
with what I'm about to say. So
uh think of me as a rock.
>> Okay.
>> And then there's this uh what do you
call those things? The you know the the
the sl Yeah.
>> Slingshot, right? Yeah.
>> So, in most cases, the slingshot is a
stick and two things that go at the top
and then there's a rubber band on each
side and then the rock. So, I feel like
my life right now, literally, I'm
stressed. I'm on edge, anxiety, I'm
unsure, I'm praying, I'm certain. I'm
I'm inspired. I'm motivated. I got all I
got this cocktail of all of these
different things that I am feeling
and I'm the rock that's inside of this
slingshot.
And the rubber band is Jesus
stretching me all the way back.
And then when he lets go,
I'm going to get thrusted
into a level
that I've been praying for, my heart has
been desiring. So being stretched
>> Mhm.
>> to the level of depletion mentally,
emotionally, financially,
psychologically.
I'm in that exact place right now.
>> 10 years from now,
what does success look like for you?
Impact.
>> Impact.
>> I'm not motivated by nothing else but
impact.
>> Impact. Define it.
>> Before I take my last breath,
I have this overwhelming sense
of getting all these visions and ideas
out
because they belong to me.
>> Yes,
>> they're mine. These are my assignments
and I'm supposed to empty myself of all
of these things and all of these
experiences that I want to create for
the world.
And that's that's what keeps me up at
night. And so I want to open a movie
studio
here in Atlanta, the one and only studio
that's actually open to the public. Mhm.
>> Um
uh on the charitable front, I got so
many more things that I want to do to
impact the world. Um from giving and
nothing temporary, something that's
going to be in place. I I want to put
trades
uh in place for for prison inmates when
they get out. teach them a trade so that
so so that the concept of them winging
it once they get out. Um because there's
so many of us that are capable of doing
it but we just don't have any trades.
Like teach me something that's connected
to how I can survive. So as the market
continues to go up and down, I'm I'm
something that's self-sufficient and
independent of a Bitcoin. Our re-entry
program has seen over 40,000 formerly
incarcerated people go through our
programs. Most of which who came out
with jobs, had their records expuned,
did family reunification,
anger management, everything was
necessary to keep them from going back.
The rate of recetivism is amazing. One
of the best in the country. uh because
we took the time to walk them through a
two-year process to help them to
acclimate. One of them, I was talking to
one of them myself. Yeah. Yeah. You're
talking to the right guy.
I was talking to one of them and and he
says, "Show me how to use a phone
>> because [clears throat] when he went in,
we had payoneses.
>> When he came out, we had Apple phones."
>> You know, uh there's so many simple
things. when when he went in uh he was
married. When he came out, he was
divorced and she was remarried. When he
went in, uh the the world was totally
different. You know, we were busing and
training. When he came out, we were
flying and now our cars are being driven
without people in them. The world is
changing so fast.
>> So fast.
>> In the midst of the change, I want to
say this to you.
I pray you find
everything
that God has for you that gives you
peace,
that gives you joy, that gives you
wholeness,
that gives you mental health,
that gives you peace,
that makes you dance in the rain.
The kind of happy
that not a scene in a movie,
just a happy man dancing in the rain.
Thank you for this time together.
in it. I really mean that for you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> I really want you to have that.
>> That was amazing.
That was amazing. That was powerful.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> That was powerful. And it was real.
It was real.
>> My honor, sir.
>> Give me a hug. Yeah. [laughter]
>> Thank you.
I hope you got something out of me.
>> Oh yeah. Beyond life my my life changed.
>> You spoke for so many men.
>> Hey everybody, I want to take this time
to thank you for watching the next
chapter podcast.
If this conversation inspired you,
helped you [music]
reflect on an idea or sparked something
new inside of you, make sure to like,
comment, and [music] subscribe so you
don't miss future episodes. Remember,
life isn't about how you begin. It's
about how you finish strong. So start
your [music] next chapter with us right
here every week.